Benten is neither tengu nor tanuki, but simply a human.
弁天とは 天狗でも狸でもない
ただの人間である
In her younger days, Benten aimlessly walked the shores of Lake Biwako
琵琶湖のほとりをぽてぽてと目的も無く歩いていた
若き日の弁天は鈴木聡美という人間の名を持ち
bearing the human name of Suzuki Satomi—
one that befit the cute country girl she was.
あくまでもそれなりに可愛い
田舎の女子にすぎなかった
Master Akadama, who happened to be
.at Lake Biwako on a New Year's visit,
その弁天を
たまたま年始の挨拶に琵琶湖に来ていた赤玉先生が
took the girl home with him.
連れて帰って来たのである
He took great care in
.giving her a tengu education,
赤玉先生は
彼女に手取り足取り天狗教育を施し
and she enthusiastically raced up
.the ladder from human to tengu.
彼女は人間から天狗への階段を
勢いよく駆け上った
Once she reached the top,
駆け上ったところで美脚を一閃
she kicked her kidnapper-turned-master to
.the curb with one flash of her gorgeous legs.
彼女は自分を連れ去り
かつ師匠ともなった赤玉先生を
蹴り落としたのである
Oh, Professor.
あら先生
You came after us, huh?
追いかけてきたのね？
The current Benten bears little
.resemblance to her former self.
今の弁天に
昔日の面影は無い
omoshiroku nai yo no naka
You just have to make
面白くない世の中
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
Original     Work
Morimi Tomihiko
"Uchouten Kazoku"
Gentousha Publishing
omoshiroku sureba ii sa
this dull world more interesting
面白くすればいいさ
omoshiroku sureba ii sa
this dull world more interesting
tsumaranee no ga kuchiguse nano wa
Some people love to claim that something is boring
“つまらねえ”のが口癖なのは
tsumaranee no ga kuchiguse nano wa
Some people love to claim that something is boring
sore koso honto ni tsumaranai
That habit is the most boring thing of all
それこそホントにつまらない
sore koso honto ni tsumaranai
That habit is the most boring thing of all
文句を言うのは簡単だけど
monku wo iu no wa kantan dakedo
It's easy to complain about stuff
dareka wa nannmo kurenai
but it doesn't do any good at all
誰かは何もくれない
dareka wa nannmo kurenai
but it doesn't do any good at all
hashiranai kedo tomari wa shinai
That sort of useless waste of time
走らないけど止まりはしない
dare ni mo nagareru ahou no chi
runs in our idiot blood
誰にも流れる阿呆の血
sawageba sawagu hodo kakitateru
Just party on and on, and the more you do
騒げば騒ぐ程かき立てる
nanto subarashiki hibi
the more awesome will be your days
なんと素晴らしき日々
omoshiroku nai yo no naka
You just have to make
面白くない世の中
omoshiroku sureba ii no sa
this dull world more interesting
面白くすればいいのさ
jibun de mitsukerya
The things you find for yourself in this world
自分で見つけりゃ
hodohodo ni paradaisu da
quickly turn it into a little paradise
ほどほどにパラダイスだ
ki ga tsukeba itsu datte
Before you know it,
気がつけば何時だって
ki ga tsukeba itsu datte
Before you know it,
uchouten jinsei da
you live a life of pure ecstasy
有頂天人生だ
uchouten jinsei da
you live a life of pure ecstasy
Episode Six
Taking in Fall Colors
ん
よ
ううん あ
よっ
ん
んっ
よっ
と
はあ
はあ ふう
ううん
えい
おっと
あ
ああ ああ
はあ
んっ
と
はあ
ん？
んん
あ
おお
おっと
あ
ああああああ
ふ あ あ？
あ
You're one active lady, Benten.
弁天さん 全くあなたときたら
アクティブだなあ
And you're pretty nimble
.yourself. For your age.
教授もお年にしては身軽ですわ
はあ
Now, just a little further.
さあ もうひと踏ん張りですよ
Sheesh. You're like a tengu.
やれやれ あなたはまるで天狗のようだな
ふう
はあ
ん
ふう
あ
ん？
I am but Suzuki Satomi.
私はただの鈴木聡美です
She bears little resemblance
.to her former self.
昔日の面影は無い
Hey.
僕ね
I was thinking about the day I first met you.
あなたと初めて会った日を思い出していた
Oh, please.
嫌ですね そんなこと忘れていいわ
Feel free to forget it.
I would never!
忘れやしない　ちょうど忘年会の日だったよ
It was at one of our year-end parties.
I heard the tanuki cage was in the inner parlor,
狸の入った檻が奥の座敷にあるというから
so I went to check on it.
様子を見に行ったんだ
あ
And you were lying next to it, sleeping peacefully.
そうしたら
あなたがその檻の側で横になって
すやすや眠っているんだな
You had piled up some
floor cushions to make a pillow
座布団を重ねて枕にして
and were curled up like a child.
子供みたいに丸まってね
Was I really?
そうでしたかしら
I thought, "Who could that be?"
誰だろうと思ったな
I didn't know the new Friday Fellow
.was a young lady.
新しく金曜倶楽部に入るのが
若い女性だとは知らなかったからな
ふう
The tanuki in the cage was
.a splendid one, and so dignified.
檻の中の狸は立派な狸で
それはもう堂々たるものだった
He didn't have the slightest hint of fear.
怖がっている様子なんか微塵も無くてね
Anyway, the tanuki and I
were staring at each other
それで僕が狸とにらめっこしていたらね
when you woke up, came over to me,
あなたが起きて僕の隣へ来て
and started talking to him.
そうして狸に喋りかけたんだ
Are you Hotei?
布袋様ですか？
I'll be meeting you officially this evening.
今宵はよろしくお願いいたします
Oh, I see!
あ そうか
You're the one Juroujin was talking about.
あなたが寿老人が言っていた人だね
I didn't know he meant a girl.
女性とは知らなくて
I'm Benten.
弁天でございます
He looks like he's sleeping well.
気持ち良さそうに寝ていますね
I feel bad that you're going to be eaten,
私に食べられるあなたが可哀想なの
but I'm still going to eat you up.
でもね 私はあなたを食べてしまうのよ
That all happened so long ago that I'd forgotten.
そんな昔のこと 忘れちゃいました
That's when I fell for you.
あの時 惚れたね
I fell in love.
恋に落ちたね
I could understand just how you felt,
あなたの気持ちが僕には分かるもの
and I thought, "Now here's a
girl after my own heart!"
ここに同志がいると思ったね
That's your own misunderstanding.
それは先生の思い違いよ
I don't remember saying anything like that.
私 そんなこと言った覚えは無いですもの
Really? I could've sworn you did.
そうかなあ
僕は覚えているんだがなあ
かあ
くう
Benten?
弁天様？
あっ
ふう
What are you doing?
何をしているんです？
Stay back, or I'll eat you.
近寄らないでちょうだい
近寄ったら喰うわよ
I'm serious.
本気よ
I don't mean to presume,
but is something the matter?
差し出がましいようですが どうしたんです？
The moon is pretty,
but I feel sad all the same.
月が綺麗で とにかく悲しくなってしまったんだもの
I want to take a bath.
お風呂に入りたい
I'm going home.
私もう帰る
Just thinking about yourself, huh?
わがままだなあ
Are you just gonna leave us on the roof?
我々は屋上に置き去りですか？
Yasaburou,
矢三郎 先生をちゃんとお送りしてね
please make sure the professor
.gets home safe and sound.
あ
ん
んん
はあ
ん？
はあ すう うう
Where did Benten go?
弁天さんはどこへ？
うう
あっと
ん？
I'm feeling hungry.
How about you?
腹が減ったね
よいしょ
Um...
ええっと んん
Have a few of these with me.
君も食べなさい
あむ
I'm pretty good at making rice balls.
僕は握り飯を作るのも上手でね
Tasty, right?
旨いだろ？
You know, I've always liked rice balls.
あむ　僕はね
握り飯が好きなんだね
They're good cold,
they're good grilled,
冷えたままでも旨いし焼いて食べても旨いし
and you can eat them
.anytime, anywhere.
いつでもどこでも食べられるからな
We call it "Benten's Early Exit."
僕らは弁天さんの途中退場という
She always disappears without warning partway through.
いつもね
彼女は断り無く途中で姿を消してしまうんだな
ん
You just can't make head or tail of her.
あの人も分からない人ですから
You're a student, right?
君は学生だろう？　彼女とどういう関係かな？
How do you know her?
We both studied under the same master.
師匠筋が同じで
Master? Master of what?
師匠 何の師匠？
Oh, is that where you learned
your act from the dinner party?
ああ さっきの宴会芸の？
Something like that.
そんなようなところで
So Benten can perform as well?
じゃあ 弁天さんも芸をやるの？
Yeah. I'm nowhere even close to her level.
私なんか足元にも及びませんよ
She's even surpassed our master.
今では師匠よりも上です
There's no one in Kyoto who can match her.
京都では敵無しです
ずず
At any rate, she sure is an eccentric beauty.
まあ とにかく一風変わった美人だよな
You're a bit of a strange one
.yourself, Professor.
先生もだいぶ変わってますな
I'm not that strange.
僕は別に変わっちゃいない
Your passion for eating is no joke.
あの食い意地の張り方はただ事じゃない
I guess you're right there.
確かに食い意地は張ってる
I've eaten so many things,
some of it for research.
いろいろなものを喰ってきたしね
半ば研究ということもあるし
ずず
You eat tanuki too.
先生は狸も喰う
Not just tanuki!
狸どころか世界中あちこち行って
I've traveled all over the world eating everything I can, be it bug, plant, beast, or fish.
昆虫でも植物でも動物でも魚でも何でも喰うよ
Are they tasty?
旨いですか
If you're going to eat something,
you have to eat it like it's tasty.
喰うからには 旨く喰ってあげる
これは喰うものの義務だ
That's our duty as people who eat.
To tell the truth, though,
しかしね君
本当のことを言えば命を喰う それだけで旨い
eating a life should be
.delicious all on its own.
That's the way it's gotta be.
こうでなくちゃいけない
僕はその境地を目指している
That's the state of mind I'm aiming for,
and that's why I eat so many things.
だからいろんなものを喰うんだよ
Well, nothing poisonous, of course.
まあ 毒がある奴はダメだけどもね
I wouldn't live to tell the tale.
死んじゃうからさ
ずず
I'm just a frog in a well, though.
しかし僕なんぞ井の中の蛙だ
If you open your eyes to the world,
世界へ目を広げてみたまえ
人間という奴は何でもかんでも喰うんだ
you'll find humans eat
.anything and everything.
It's amazing how much of a
.passion for eating we have.
呆れるぐらい食い意地が張ってるんだ
Whenever I think of it,
I'm filled with admiration.
それを考えると僕は決まって感服するな
To eat is to love.
喰うということは愛するということだよ
We eat so many things!
我々はなんと様々なものを喰うのだろう
And we love so many things!
そして我々はなんと様々なものを愛するのだろう
Hooray for humanity!
人間万歳！
That's how you start to feel.
という気持ちになるんだな
I don't think the ones being eaten
.are quite so exuberant about it.
でも喰われる側にしたら 万歳どころじゃないな
Oh, I'm sure they must hate it, of course.
喰われるものはそりゃあもちろん嫌に決まってる
I wouldn't like to have a bear or
.a wolf bite my head off either.
僕だって熊や狼に
ガリガリ頭からかじられるのは嫌だからな
No one would.
皆 嫌だよ
But if they're going to be eaten anyway,
I'd like to be the one to eat them.
でも喰われちまうのだし 僕は喰いたいな
I feel bad for them, but I like tanuki
.so much I want to eat them up.
可哀想だけれども
食べちゃいたいほど狸が好きだしな
はむ
は
Not just tanuki, either.
狸に限らない かわゆきものたちを我々は喰うんだ
We'll eat all the cute li'l critters out there.
It's a shame, but they're just so delicious.
悲しいけれども実に旨い
A fine contradiction, wouldn't you say?
ここらへんは大いなる矛盾だな
Just like love!
即ち愛だ
I'm not entirely sure,
but it's probably love, right?
ん よく分からんが多分 愛だね
Yeah, must be.
これが愛だね
Humans don't have to worry about being eaten,
so they can afford to be nonchalant about it.
人間は喰われる心配が無いから
そんなのんきなことを言う
You're firmly on the side of the eaten, I see.
やけに君は喰われる側の肩を持つね
But that's a good point.
しかし大事なことだものな
You're right that we humans don't
.have to worry about being eaten.
確かに僕らのような人間には喰われる心配がない
No natural enemies.
天敵がいない
We die, get burned, turn to ashes,
死んで焼かれて灰になって
get eaten by microbes,
and return to dust. That's about it.
微生物に喰われて土に還るぐらいだ
But thinking about it that way makes me sad.
でもそうなると僕には寂しいという気持ちが起こるな
It's a bit pitiful just being
eaten by microbes, right?
いきなり微生物に喰われるのは寂しいんだな
If I'm gonna die one day anyway—
どうせ死ぬのなら
well, as long as it doesn't hurt too much—
あんまり痛くさえなければね
I'd rather be eaten by a tanuki.
僕は狸に喰われるのがいいんだ
ん う え？
I'd rather be a tanuki's dinner
.than die all wrinkly in a hospital.
病院でしわくちゃになって死ぬよりも
狸の晩ご飯になる方がいい
Dying in a hospital doesn't nourish anyone.
病院で死んだって誰の栄養にもならない
That's so sad.
そんなのは寂しいね
I'd much rather fill a tanuki's stomach, at least.
狸が腹を膨らましてくれる方がよっぽどいいな
I think any tanuki who ate you would be
.biting off more than he could chew.
先生を喰うのは
ちと狸の手に余りますな
Guess so.
そうだね
Not to mention, I bet I would taste horrible.
それに僕はきっと不味い気がするんだ
What a pity.
悲しいなあ
Isn't it sad that someone would just
assume that they'd taste bad to a tanuki?
狸たちが自分を喰ってもまずかろう
そう思う人間っていうのは悲しいなあ
I've never heard of any human
.getting sad about something like that.
そんなことで悲しむ人間なんか聞いたこともない
There was a tanuki who said something like that to me back then, too.
そういうことを僕に言った狸がいたんだよね
I can remember it even now.
それを今でも思い出す
え？
Kyoto Newspaper HQ
Town Welfare Hall
Dotemachi St.
It was the night Benten first
.joined the Friday Fellows.
弁天さんが初めて金曜倶楽部に
迎えられた夜のことだ
You're really something, huh?
君は大したもんだね
狸社会ではきっと名のある狸なのだろうな
You must have really made a name
.for yourself among tanuki-kind.
今宵 我々は君を喰うことになっている
This evening, we'll be eating you.
You're probably a bit reluctant,
君としちゃあ不本意だろうが
but we always have tanuki stew
.at our year-end party.
我々の忘年会は狸鍋と決まっているからな
Being born as a tanuki means there may come
.a time when you'll be eaten by humans.
狸として生まれたからには
人間に喰われることもあるさ
This may be selfish of me,
しかしね 手前勝手ではあるけれども
but I'm happy I get to eat you.
僕は君を喰うことができて嬉しく思っているんだよ
It gives meaning to the fact that we met.
これもまた一つの出会いだからね
How can you be so calm?
君は何故そんなに落ち着いているのかね
Aren't you anxious?
不安じゃないのかな
I've done everything I wanted to do.
俺はこれまでにやりたいことは全てやり
子供たちも大きくなった
My children have grown up.
The youngest is still small,
but he has his brothers,
末はまだ小さいけれども
兄たちがいるから
-後は助け合って立派にやってゆくであろう
-あ ああ ああ
so I suppose all that remains is for them to
.help each other out and live decent lives.
I sowed my seeds and nurtured them, to an extent.
俺は種を撒き そこそこ育てた
I've fulfilled my role as a tanuki.
一匹の狸としての役目は全うしたのだ
The rest of my days are a blessing,
残された日々は天恵である
つまりは儲けものである
or in other words, a lucky break.
従ってまあ ここであなた方に喰われたところで
一向に構わない
Therefore, at this point,
I don't mind being eaten by you at all.
If you want to eat me, you should.
喰いたければ喰うが良い
何だか妙だな 君が喋っているような気がするんだが
This is kind of weird.
I get the feeling you're talking,
but it must be my imagination.
妄想だろうか
I really am talking.
現に俺は喋っているよ
Well, I'll be!
参るね あんまり人をびっくりさせるもんじゃない
You shouldn't surprise people like that.
I just figured it wouldn't matter
.if I said something to you.
あなたならば喋っても構わんかなと ふと思ったのだ
Call it the last trick of my life.
我が生涯最後のいたずらと言うべきか
A reflection of my idiot blood.
阿呆の血のしからしむるところだ
あ
それからしばらくの間 話をしたよ
And then we talked for a bit
about where we lived, what kinds of
.things we ate, that kind of stuff.
どこに住んでんだとか どんなものを喰ってんだとかね
ただ一点
But there was one thing.
The tanuki was worried he might taste bad.
その狸は 自分は不味いのではないか
ということを気にしていた
大丈夫だ　僕が責任を持つ
Don't worry.
I'll be certain to make a delicious stew out of you.
美味しい鍋にしてやる
Please see it through from beginning to end.
是非とも首尾よくやっていただきたい
せっかくの鍋を台無しにしては申し訳ないからな
I would feel terrible if I ruined
.an otherwise tasty stew.
You're a magnificent tanuki,
so I'm sure you'll taste great.
君は立派な狸だから美味しいよ 安心したまえ
Don't worry.
As a last request, mind telling me your name?
冥土の土産にあなたのお名前を伺いたい
I'm Yodogawa Choutarou.
淀川長太郎という者だ
ん
やはり あなたがそうであったか
Just as I thought. It is you.
おや？
Oh?
You know me?
僕を知っているのかい？
身内が世話になったものでね
You helped out one of my family members.
Would you tell me your name in return?
お返しに君の名前も教えてくれよ
私は偽右衛門 下鴨総一郎だ
I'm the Nise-emon, Shimogamo Souichirou.
Who's there?
どなた？
あ
うん？
あれ？
Huh?
うん？
確か今 あれ？
Wasn't he just...
You probably find it hard to believe
a weird story like that, right?
こんな奇天烈な話 君は信じまいね
信じてもいいな
I think I can manage.
I'm glad to hear it.
嬉しいね 君と僕の仲だから話したのさ
I told you because I felt this
.connection between us.
Uh, we just met for the first time tonight.
今宵 会ったばかりですぜ？
But I feel like we're destined
.to really know each other.
僕は君に運命を感じた
A chance meeting is a meeting
.brought about by fate, after all.
袖擦り合うも多生の縁と言う
今宵の出会いに乾杯だ
Let's drink to this evening's encounter! A toast!
乾杯
大学教授ともあろう人が
Is it okay for a supposed
college professor like you
to be drinking in a place like this
in the middle of the night?
夜中にこんな所でお酒を飲んでいいんですか
Don't you worry about that.
構わん構わん
It's just a reflection of my idiot blood!
阿呆の血のしからしむるところさ
あ
Hey, you!
おおい君
What do you know? A ladder!
こんな所にはしごが
We can get down this way.
これで降りられる
Phew. That was lucky.
いやあ助かった助かった
よっと
ん
あ
海星？　君か？
Kaisei, is that you?
Go home and get some sleep, you blockhead.
さっさと帰って寝ちまえ このあほんだら
Next time, you're on your own.
次はもう助けないよ
おおい 寺町通りはこっちだよね
Hey, Teramachi Street is this way, right?
ありがとう
Thanks.
The
Six
Paths
ひ
It's me, big bro.
兄さん 俺だよ
なんだ矢三郎かよ
Oh geez, Yasaburou?
生きてたか 心配したんだぜ
So you're still alive, then. I was worried.
Surprisingly enough, yeah.
どっこい生きてる
You gonna abandon the world and become a frog too?
お前も世を捨てて蛙になる気かい？
我が子が二匹も蛙になったら母上が泣く
If two of her sons ended up
.as frogs, Mother would cry.
一晩泊めてもらうだけさ
I'm just gonna crash for the night.
That's fine.
そんならいいや　悩み事でもあるのかと思ったよ
I thought you might have been
.worrying about something.
お前はちっこい頃からそういうことを
口にしない奴だったけれど
You've had trouble talking about things
.that bother you ever since you were little.
悩みなど皆無だ
I'll have you know I never worry.
面白おかしく生きると決めたのだから
My life is far too interesting
.and amusing for that.
Are you drunk?
飲んできたのか
Yep.
うん
Come visit me at my office sometime.
今度ぜひ研究室に遊びにおいで
Kyoto University
Yodogawa Choutarou
それではな また会おうな
Well then, be seeing you.
それは阿呆の血のしからしむるところだって
He said it was a "reflection"
of his "idiot blood."
この淀川という大学教授が父上と同じことを言うんだ
This university professor, Yodogawa,
said the same thing Father used to.
ふむ
母上を救った恩人ではあっても 相手は憎むべき仇だ
Even if we owe him for saving Mother,
by rights, we should hate him as an enemy.
でも 何故か慕わしく思えた
But for some reason,
I think of him affectionately,
妙な話だけど
as strange as that may be.
俺はつくづく不思議だよ
I find it utterly bizarre.
何故俺は彼を憎まないのだろうか
Why don't I hate him?
俺はあの教授がとても好きになってしまったし
To be honest, I like him a lot.
And why do I have such a crush on Benten,
父上を鍋にして喰ってしまった弁天様に
when she ate Father in a stew?
何故 俺は惚れたりするのかね
そりゃお前 阿呆の血のしからしむるところさ
It's obviously another
.reflection of our idiot blood.
Besides, we're tanuki.
それに俺たちは狸だからな
We just get eaten every now and then.
たまには喰われることもあるさ
It's not wrong for a human to eat a tanuki.
人間が狸を喰うのは間違ってはいないよ
I admire you, big bro.
兄さんは偉いな 悟っているな
You're enlightened.
Not at all.
いや 実のところ俺は
分かったようなふりをしているだけだよ
To tell the truth,
I just act like I know it all.
I'm just a frog in a well, after all.
なにせ井の中の蛙だもの
またそうやって逃げを打つ
You always use that
convenient excuse, huh?
Not at all. I still have a lot to learn.
そうではない 未熟者だよ 俺なんぞ
Even now, I tear up when I think of Father.
俺は今でも父上のことを考えると涙が出るさ
また誰かが悩み事の相談かい？
Is someone here to talk to you
about their troubles?
No. That's Benten.
いや あれは弁天様だな
What?
え？
彼女は何も喋らない
She never says anything.
She just sits there like that,
crying all alone.
ああしていつも１人で泣いているんだ
The well water is gonna get all salty.
井戸水が塩辛くなっちまう
I wonder why she cries.
何故泣くんだろう？
I wonder what she's sad about.
何が悲しいというんだろう？
綺麗な月を見たせいかな
Could it be because the moon's so pretty?
子供というのは訳も無く泣くものさ
Children don't have to cry
.for a reason. They just do.
Back then, in the heart of the city,
その頃 洛中では
my big brother Yaichirou
and my uncle Ebisugawa Soun
我が兄の矢一郎と
叔父である夷川早雲による
次期偽右衛門を巡る醜い争いが始まっていたという
were starting up the unsightly battle
.over who would be the next Nise-emon.
But as for me,
だが
私といえば
およそ大海を知らない
I knew nothing of the outside world.
井戸の中の蛙であった
I was just a frog in a well.
繋いだ手を振りほどけば
You shake off my hand
tsunaida te wo furihodokeba
いたずらに　君微笑む
and idly smile at me
itazura ni kimi hohoemu
春は嵐　ざわざわする
Spring is ripe with the roll of thunder,
haru wa arashi zawazawa suru
もう花びら散りすぼんだ
and some cherry blossoms have already left the branches
mou hanabira chirisubonda
口癖はケセラセラ
Your favorite phrase is "Que será, será"
kuchiguse wa que sera sera
また呟く声がする
I can hear you whisper it again
mata tsubuyaku koe ga suru
彼女はいつもさよなら言わずに
She always vanishes
kanojo wa itsumo
sayonara
without saying "Goodbye,"
iwazu ni
風と消える
just like the wind
kaze to kieru
I don't know what the future will be like,
mirai no koto wa wakaranai keredo
未来のことはわからないけれど
今ここにある奇蹟は
but I'll have faith
ima koko ni aru
that little miracles
kiseki wa
僕のものと信じてる
are awaiting me
boku no mono to shinjiteru
約束なんてしたくないけれど
I don't want to be tied down by promises,
yakusoku nante shitakunai keredo
but let's hold up our hands
sono te wo kazashite
その手をかざして確かなもの
and find something,
tashika na mono
手に入れよう
something permanent
te ni ireyou
それは僕らを輝かす
that will
sore wa
show just who we are
bokura wo kagayakasu
ええい どいつもこいつもマナーがなってない
Argh, none of these schmucks have any manners!
あ そこ 湯船にタオルをつけるな
Like that! Don't wear a towel in the bathtub!
Next Time:
Bathhouse Rules